A Guide to the National Committee on United States-China Relations records, RG 3, Accession 3 FA1185
Rockefeller Archive Center
National Committee on United States-China Relations records, RG 3, Accession 3
1973-2014
Rockefeller Archive Center
National Committee on United States-China Relations, Inc.
FA1185
13.64 Cubic Feet 34 document boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact an RAC archivist for further instruction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The National Committee on United States-China Relations donated its records to the Rockefeller Archive Center by deed of gift dated March 27, 2015.
Biographical / Historical
The National Committee on United States – China Relations (NCUSCR) was established in 1966 as a nonprofit educational organization with a mission to encourage mutual understanding and dialogue between citizens of the United States and China.
The National Committee came into being through the cooperative efforts of scholars and civic, religious, and business leaders who, at a time of mutual hostility between the two countries, sought to stimulate public discussion about China and the United States' relations with it by sponsoring conferences, seminars, publications, and other education and outreach programs. In 1972, the National Committee sponsored the Chinese table tennis team's historic U. S. visit. This round of "Ping Pong Diplomacy," which followed closely on Richard Nixon's visit to China in February 1972, helped pave the way for later exchanges and, eventually, for the normalization of relations with China in 1979. Building on these cultural exchanges, the National Committee came to be a primary organizer of professional and policy exchanges between the two countries (and including Hong Kong and Taiwan), in the areas of foreign affairs and international relations, economic development, governance and legal affairs, education, mass media, environmental and global issues, etc. As its role in exchanges became more prominent, the National Committee turned over some of its educational programs to the Asia Society in the late 1970s, but it continues its educational role through public education events and ongoing outreach.
Funding for the National Committee comes from the United States government (especially the Department of State), corporations, and foundations, as well as from its individual membership.
Arrangement
The records of the National Committee on United States – China Relations are divided into ten record groups, which reflect the order in which the records were received (but which are otherwise an artificial distinction). The records are sorted intellectually into series, which carry over through all record groups, but they have received little or no physical rearrangement. RG 3 of the NCUSCR records contains records from seven series: 1 – Events; 2 – Exchanges - General; 3 - Exchanges to China; 4 – Exchanges from China; 6 – Publications and Reports; 8 - Programs, Projects, and Proposals; and 9 – Ping Pong Diplomacy.
The RG 3 accession also includes a few boxes of audiovisual materials, which, pending further processing, have not been included in the FA1185 finding aid. They will be arranged and described with other, related audiovisual materials in a subsequent record group and finding aid.
Scope and Contents
RG 3 of the NCUSCR records documents the National Committee's ongoing work on behalf of cross-cultural orientation and understanding through its Scholar and Teachers Orientation Programs, Fulbright-Hays Summer Seminars, Student Leaders Exchange, and Young Leaders Forums in particular. Materials in the Exchanges from China series document the visits of athletic teams and other delegations from China in 1976–1978 and 1980. Also in the Programs, Projects, and Proposals series are records relating to the National Committee's "China Town Hall: Local Connections, National Reflections" webcasts and conversations on China, especially in 2007–2008; and files relating to the surveys it conducted for the Ford Foundation and the MacArthur Foundation, 2002–2007, on the topic of U. S. – China / International Relations and Security Issues. The Publications series includes National Committee brochures from 1973 – 2014, and its China Policy Series pamphlets from 1989-2007.
The RG 3 accession includes a few boxes of audiovisual materials that have not been included in this finding aid. The recordings – including the 2003 U. S. Foreign Policy Colloquium; China Conversations programs; and the Ping Pong matches in 1972 – pending processing, will be arranged and described with other, related audiovisual materials in a subsequent record group and finding aid.
- Events, 1993; 1
  - Scholar Orientation Program Reunion, 1993 April 4 (Box 27, Folder 240)
    Scope and Contents
    Beijing. Reunion held on occasion of the fourteenth year of the program. Includes background and planning correspondence.
- Exchanges - General, 1982-1984, 1997-2010, 2013; 2
  The Exchanges - General series in RG 3 contains records of the National Committee's Young Leaders Forum, from 2001 to 2013, and of its Teachers Orientation Program, from 1997 to 2004.
  Established in 2002 in partnership with the Chinese People's Institute of Foreign Affairs and still ongoing, the annual Young Leaders Forum (YLF) brings together a select group of American and Chinese young professionals for a four- or five-day retreat at sites that alternate between the U. S. and China. Organized around a theme, meetings seek to develop mutual understanding and personal connections and dialogue among fellows, who represent not only two countries and cultures, but also a diverse range of professional backgrounds and interests.
  Starting in 1997, the Teachers Orientation Program organized a separate two-week study tour on American History and Culture for Chinese participants in the Teachers Exchange Program, established in 1996. Modeled on the Scholar Orientation Program (SOP) (see the Programs, Projects, and Proposals series), Teachers Orientation Program trips were numbered in a consecutive series with their SOP counterparts. RG 3 documents the TOP program from 1997 – 2004 (SOP numbers 76 – 77, 80, 83, and 85 – 87). Additional materials concerning Teachers Orientation programs and records of study tours from 2006 – 2009 are found in RG 1 (FA772).
  - Young Leaders Forum: General Planning and Program, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Meetings and Chronological File, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Honorary Advisors, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    Invitations and Bios.
  - Young Leaders Forum: Sponsors, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Nominees (U.S. and China), 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Selection of Fellows, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Invitations, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Program Ideas, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Speakers, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Entertainment Activities, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Includes photos of Channel Cat yacht.
  - Young Leaders Forum: Hotel Arrangements, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Includes photos of El Encanto Hotel, Santa Barbara, CA.
  - Young Leaders Forum: Beijing Dinner, 2002 February 22 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Deng Rong Visit, 2002 June (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Program Assessments and Report, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Candidates Book, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
    Pages removed from ring binder.
  - Young Leaders Forum: General Program and Planning, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 21-22)
    The 2003 forum met October 31 - November 4 in Huangshan and Hangzhou and brought together fellows from the 2002 and 2003 cohorts. The meeting had originally been planned for April, but the outbreak of SARS caused its postponement.
  - Young Leaders Forum: Sponsorship and Funding, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Invitations (Fellows and Honorary Advisors), 2003 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Includes some potential candidates.
  - Young Leaders Forum: Report and Evaluations, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Prospective Candidates File, 2004-2006 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Candidates (by Sector), 2005 (Box 4, Folder 27-28)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Candidates Book, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 29-30)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Briefing Materials (Volumes 1 and 2), 2006 (Box 4, Folder 31-32)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Candidates Book (by Sector), 2007 (Box 4, Folder 33-34)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Prospective Candidates File, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Prospective Candidates (by Sector), 2008 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Candidates, 2009 (Box 5, Folder 37-38)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Candidates, 2010 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Young Leaders Forum: Candidates, 2013 (Box 5, Folder 40-41)
  - Luce Chinese Scholars, 1982-1984 (Box 18, Folder 145)
  - FA1185:004 - Luce Chinese Scholars, 1982-1984; Still Image: Two 3x5 color prints. (Box 34, Folder 145)
    Yuan Jihui with unidentified woman at dinner in honor of Luce Scholars, Jund 23, 1983.
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 76): General, 1997 June 29-July 12 (Box 22, Folder 192)
    Program cosponsored with the American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS). Education and American Studies. Program for Chinese secondary school teachers in the U. S. on a teachers exchange program. Namelist and Itinerary.
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 76): Correspondence, 1997 June 29-July 12 (Box 22, Folder 193)
    Program cosponsored with the American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS). Education and American Studies. ACLS and Escort correspondence and Thank Yous.
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 76): Programming and Planning, 1997 June 29-July 12 (Box 22, Folder 194)
    Program cosponsored with the American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS). Education and American Studies. Includes invoices.
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 76): Evaluation Forms, 1997 June 29-July 12 (Box 22, Folder 195)
    Program cosponsored with the American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS). Education and American Studies.
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 77), 1998 June 28-July 11 (Box 22, Folder 196)
    Program cosponsored with the American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS). Education and American Studies. For report, see Scholar Orientation Program (No. 78).
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 80): General, 1999 July 1-10 (Box 23, Folder 205)
    Program in Education and American Studies, conducted for the American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS).
  - FA1185:019 - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 80): General, 1999 July 1-10; Still Images: 3 4x6 color prints. (Box 34, Folder 205)
    Three group photos of delegation
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 80): Background and Planning, 1999 July 1-10 (Box 23, Folder 206)
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 80): Mailing Lists and Application Inquiries, 1999 July 1-10 (Box 23, Folder 207)
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 80): Programming and Visit Planning, 1999 July 1-10 (Box 23, Folder 208)
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 80): Evaluations, 1999 July 1-10 (Box 23, Folder 209)
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 83): Namelists, Itinerary, and Participant Correspondence, 2000 July 2-12 (Box 25, Folder 219)
    Program conducted for the American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS).
  - FA1185:020 - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 83): Namelists, Itinerary, and Participant Correspondence, 2000 July 2-12; Still image: 105 color prints 3x5 - 4x6, plus negatives. (Box 34, Folder 219)
    Photos of delegates' visits to Virginia, Washington, DC, and New York. Includes some duplicates.
  - FA1185:021 - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 83): Namelists, Itinerary, and Participant Correspondence, 2000 July 2-12; Still image: 4x6 color print mounted on sheet of paper. (Box 34, Folder 219)
    Group photo of delegation at Williamsburg, with identifications.
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 83): Correspondence, 2000 July 2-12 (Box 25, Folder 220)
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 83): Background Readings, 2000 July 2-12 (Box 25, Folder 221)
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 83): Programming and Visit Planning, 2000 July 2-12 (Box 25, Folder 222)
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 83): Evaluations, 2000 July 2-12 (Box 25, Folder 223)
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 85): Namelists, Itinerary, and Correspondence, 2001 July 1-11 (Box 26, Folder 229)
    Cosponsored with the American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS)
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 85): Programming and Visit Planning, 2001 July 1-11 (Box 26, Folder 230)
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 86): Namelist, Itinerary, and Correspondence, 2002 June 30-July 10 (Box 26, Folder 231)
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 86): Programming and Visit Planning, 2002 June 30-July 10 (Box 26, Folder 232)
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 86): Evaluations, 2002 June 30-July 10 (Box 26, Folder 233)
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 87): General, 2003 June 29-July 9 (Box 26, Folder 234)
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 87): Background and Planning, 2003 June 29-July 9 (Box 26, Folder 235)
    Includes 2003 itinerary, as well as sample itineraries from 1999-2002.
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 87): Programming and Visit Planning, 2003 June 29-July 9 (Box 27, Folder 236)
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 87): Evaluations, 2003 June 29-July 9 (Box 27, Folder 237)
  - Teachers Orientation Program (SOP No. 85 - SOP No. 87): Background Readings, 2001-2003 (Box 27, Folder 238)
    Packet of background readings on U.S. government and on history of places and institutions visited during the orientation program. File combines materials from three years of the program.
  - Teachers Orientation Program, 2004 June 27-July 7 (Box 27, Folder 239)
    Includes evaluations, visit planning, and hotel arrangements. File does not includes an itinerary or namelist.
  - National Anthems, Undated (Box 33, Folder 313)
    Scores and recordings of the National Anthem of the People's Republic of China; recording of the Star Spangled Banner and other patriotic songs.
  - FA1185:035 - National Anthems, Undated; AV: Three 7" record discs, with sleeves. (Box FA1185:035, Folder 313)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
    Two 33 and a third rpm 7" record discs, recorded in China; one 45 rpm record.
- Exchanges to China, 1977, 1991-2008, 2013; 3
  The Exchanges to China series in RG 3 contains records and briefing materials for participants in the Student Leaders Exchange, 2004 – 2007, and 2013. Begun in 2004, the Student Leaders Exchange program sponsored twelve U. S. high-school students (Presidential Scholars) annually on a two-week study trip to China (reciprocal visits from China began in 2007). The series also includes Curriculum Projects created by participants in Fulbright-Hays Seminars Abroad, for 1991, 1994-1998, and 2002. One final file relates to the State Education Leaders Delegation, which traveled to China in 1977.
  - Student Leaders Exchange (Briefing Book), 2004 July 16-31 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Student Leaders Exchange, 2004-2007 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    Includes evaluations for 2006 - 2007.
  - Student Leaders Exchange, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 43A)
    Restricted - Confidential material - Open in 2028.
  - Student Leaders Exchange (Briefing Book), 2007 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    Jon Lowet copy.
  - Student Leaders Exchange (Briefing Book, Section 3), 2013 June-July (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Congressional Staff Delegation (Briefing Book, Section 3), 2008 December (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Fulbright-Hays Seminars Abroad: Curriculum Projects, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 47-48)
    China: Tradition and Transformation. Fulbright Summer Seminar.
  - Fulbright-Hays Seminars Abroad: Curriculum Projects, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 49-50)
  - Fulbright-Hays Seminars Abroad: Curriculum Projects, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Fulbright-Hays Seminars Abroad: Curriculum Projects, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 52-55)
  - Fulbright-Hays Seminars Abroad: Curriculum Projects, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 56-57)
  - Fulbright-Hays Seminars Abroad: Curriculum Projects, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 58-59)
  - Fulbright-Hays Seminars Abroad: Curriculum Projects, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 60-63)
  - Fulbright-Hays Seminars Abroad: Curriculum Projects, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 64)
  - Fulbright-Hays Seminars Abroad: Curriculum Projects, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 65-66)
  - Fulbright- Hays Seminars Abroad: Curriculum Projects, 2002 (Box 9, Folder 67-69)
  - State Education Leaders Delegation: General, 1977 October 28-November 15 (Box 30, Folder 267)
    Background and Planning; draft of report preface and contract for publication of China's Schools in Flux (1978).
- Exchanges from China, 1976-1978, 1980; 4
  The Exchanges from China series contains records of delegations from 1976 – 1978 and 1980, documenting, notably, the visits of several sports teams (Volleyball, Soccer, Basketball, and Diving), and the visit of a high-level delegation from the Chinese People's Institute of Foreign Affairs. Other files concern visits from the Ministry of Culture, the Chinese International Travel Bureau (Luxingshe), an Urban Transportation delegation, and other educational and cultural delegations.
  - Chinese Diving Team and Coaches Visit, 1980 April 21-May 15 (Box 9, Folder 70)
  - Vocational Education Delegation, 1980 May 6-27 (Box 10, Folder 71-72)
  - University Librarians Delegation: General, 1980 June 27-July 19 (Box 10, Folder 73)
  - University Librarians Delegation: Report, Thank Yous, and Follow-Up, 1980 June 27-July 19 (Box 10, Folder 74)
  - Ministry of Culture Delegation: General, 1980 July 3-19 (Box 10, Folder 75)
    Visit of Liu Fuzhi, Senior Vice Minister of Culture, and Cultural Delegation.
  - Ministry of Culture Delegation: Meetings and Visits, 1980 July 3-19 (Box 10, Folder 76-78)
    Includes materials in Chinese. Includes promotional photos from Universal Studios.
  - Ministry of Culture Delegation: Report and Thank Yous, 1980 July 3-19 (Box 10, Folder 79)
  - Urban Transportation Delegation, 1980 July 6-28 (Box 10, Folder 80)
    Co-sponsored with the Cooper Union Research Foundation.
  - Urban Transportation Delegation, 1980 July 6-28 (Box 11, Folder 81)
  - FA1185:001 - Urban Transportation Delegation, 1980 July 6-28; Still Image: 10 black and white snapshots. (Box 34, Folder 81)
    10 images of Janet Cady with Chinese friends, Shanghai, June 6, 1981, enclosed in letter from Lao Yuan-sheng, June 23, 1981.
  - Adult Education Delegation: General, 1980 September 19-October 11 (Box 11, Folder 82)
  - Adult Education Delegation: Report, Thank Yous, and Follow-Up, 1980 September 19-October 11 (Box 11, Folder 83)
  - Printing and Publications Delegation: General, 1980 October 5-25 (Box 11, Folder 84)
  - Printing and Publications Delegation: Background Materials, 1980 October 5-25 (Box 11, Folder 85)
  - Printing and Publications Delegation: Visits, 1980 October 5-25 (Box 11, Folder 86)
  - Printing and Publications Delegation: Report and Follow-Up, 1980 October 5-25 (Box 11, Folder 87)
  - FA1185:002-003 - Printing and Publications Delegation: Report and Follow-Up, 1980 October 5-25; Still Image: 4 black and white snapshots. (Box 34, Folder 87)
    Unidentified images.
  - General Administration of Travel and Tourism Delegation (Luxingshe): General, 1980 October 6-27 (Box 11, Folder 88)
  - General Administration of Travel and Tourism Delegation (Luxingshe): Meetings and Visits, 1980 October 6-27 (Box 11, Folder 89)
  - General Administration of Travel and Tourism Delegation (Luxingshe): Meetings and Visits, 1980 October 6-27; Still Image: 5 black and white prints. (Box 12, Folder 90)
    Includes photos of Royal Hawaiian and Sheraton Waikiki hotels.
  - General Administration of Travel and Tourism Delegation (Luxingshe): Report, Itinerary, Thank Yous, and Folllow-Up, 1980 October 6-27 (Box 12, Folder 91)
  - Travel and Tourism and Printing and Publications Delegations: Welcome Banquet, 1980 October 7 (Box 12, Folder 92)
  - Cinema Delegation, 1980 November 13-December 3 (Box 12, Folder 93-94)
  - Men's and Women's Volleyball Teams: Background and Pre-Trip Planning, 1976 October 2-17 (Box 27, Folder 241)
  - Men's and Women's Volleyball Teams: Budgets and Contracts, 1976 October 2-17 (Box 27, Folder 242)
  - Men's and Women's Volleyball Teams: Player Information and Program Booklet, 1976 October 2-17 (Box 27, Folder 243)
  - FA1185:022 - Men's and Women's Volleyball Teams: Player Information and Program Booklet, 1976 October 2-17; Still Images: Black and white images, 3x5, 8x10, and 8.5 x 14 roster sheet (Box 34, Folder 243)
    Press photo of U. S. women's team in match; group photo of U. S. men's team; Roster of Men's and Women's Volleyball delegation from China (headshot photos and identifications glued to 8.5 x 14 sheet.
  - Men's and Women's Volleyball Teams: Press Releases and Publicity, 1976 October 2-17 (Box 27, Folder 244)
    Also includes some general material on sports in China.
  - FA1185:023 - Men's and Women's Volleyball Teams: Press Releases and Publicity, 1976 October 2-17; Still Images: 8x10 black and white glossy print and copy negative; 5 color slides (Box 34, Folder 244)
    Print and color slides of unidentified women's volleyball match, copyright 1976, Liu Heung Shing.
  - FA1185:027 - Men's and Women's Volleyball Teams: Press Releases and Publicity, 1976 October 2-17; Oversized: Newspaper (Box FA1185:027, Folder 244)
    China Daily News, vol. 37, no. 25, 1976 October 6. Presumably includes coverage of Chinese Volleyball Teams.
  - Men's and Women's Volleyball Teams: Visits and Matches, 1976 October 2-17 (Box 28, Folder 245)
  - FA1185:028 - Men's and Women's Volleyball Teams: Visits and Matches, 1976 October 2-17; Oversized: Color poster 28" x 44" (Box FA1185:028, Folder 245)
    USA-China Volleyball, Men and Women, El Paso County Coliseum, Oct. 10, 1976
  - Men's and Women's Volleyball Teams: Thank You's, 1976 October 2-17 (Box 28, Folder 246)
  - Chinese People's Institute of Foreign Affairs Delegation: General, 1977 June 27-July 19 (Box 28, Folder 247)
    Itineraries, Background and Planning, Brochure, and Hotel and Travel Arrangements
  - Chinese People's Institute of Foreign Affairs Delegation: Budgets, 1977 June 27-July 19 (Box 28, Folder 248)
  - Chinese People's Institute of Foreign Affairs Delegation: Transcripts of Speeches, Discussions, and Presentations, 1977 June 27-July 19 (Box 28, Folder 249)
  - Chinese People's Institute of Foreign Affairs Delegation: Visits (Washington, DC), 1977 June 27-July 19 (Box 28, Folder 250)
  - Chinese People's Institute of Foreign Affairs Delegation: Visits (New York), 1977 June 27-July 19 (Box 28, Folder 251)
  - Chinese People's Institute of Foreign Affairs Delegation: Media Luncheon (New York, 1977 July 7), 1977 June 27-July 19 (Box 29, Folder 252)
    File consists mainly of invitation and guest lists.